Guide to the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories 2008.030
Brooklyn Historical Society
Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories
2007 - 2008
2008
Brooklyn Historical Society
Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Sullivan, Sady
Williams, Bahati
2008.030
32.27 Gigabytes in 236 files, total running time: 48 hours, 18 minutes, 21 seconds; 1 linear foot in one record box
Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS) and Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation (Restoration) partnered on the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral history project in 2007-2008 to celebrate the fortieth anniversary of Restoration's founding as the first community development corporation (CDC) in the United States. Nearly sixty interviews were conducted with founding Board members, supporters, activists, artists, tenants, and other community members. Audio clips from these oral history interviews were included in the exhibit Reflections on Community Development: Stories from Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation (BHS 2008, Restoration 2009).
Historical note
History of Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation, excerpted from their website: In 1964, with the cooperation of Senator Jacob K. Javits and Mayor John W. Lindsay, Senator Robert F. Kennedy set into motion a round of legislative action that created the Special Impact Program, an amendment to the Economic Opportunity Act of 1964. He announced a seven point action plan that would serve as a national model for community development. The plan called for the formation of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Renewal and Rehabilitation Corporation and the Development Services Corporation in Brooklyn, New York, involving assistance from some of the foremost leaders of the American business community.
Under the leadership of Judge Thomas R. Jones, in 1967 the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation (Restoration) was formally established to consolidate and carry forward these efforts. One year later, Restoration purchased an abandoned milk bottling plant in the heart of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, Sheffield Farms, to serve as its new corporate headquarters. Renovations soon began to create what became the community center Restoration Plaza. Since 1967, Restoration has catalyzed enormous economic, cultural, and educational improvements in Central Brooklyn.*
Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral history at Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS): BHS and Restoration partnered on the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral history project in 2007-2008 to celebrate the fortieth anniversary of Restoration's founding as the first community development corporation (CDC) in the United States. Nearly sixty interviews were conducted with founding Board members, supporters, activists, artists, tenants, and other community members. Audio clips from these oral history interviews were included in the exhibition Reflections on Community Development: Stories from Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation (BHS 2008, Restoration 2009). The exhibition provided a local and national narrative of the rise and importance of CDCs from their inception during the late 1960s to four decades later, using Restoration as a case study.
*"History." Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration. http://www.restorationplaza.org/about/history.
Scope and Contents
This collection of oral history recordings attempts to tell the story of a forty-year-old community institution, Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation, through the diverse voices of board members, staff, artists, business owners, community activists, homeowners, and young students of the institution's cultural programming. In documenting that story, a roughly sketched parallel story emerges that chronicles the culture of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood and surrounding neighborhoods of Brooklyn. Additionally, the more substantive interviews offer the more traditional oral history of an individual in addition to that of the institution. Narrators are often residents of Bedford-Stuyvesant and give their insight into predecessor or concurrent organizations such as Youth in Action, Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation, Weeksville Heritage Center, Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association, and the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council. The interviews also inform an understanding of the inner workings of Restoration and its effects on the community; including initiatives such as establishing Restoration Plaza and offices for the nonprofit, the Center for Arts and Culture, the Billie Holiday Theatre, Skylight Gallery, Youth Arts Academy, and the Weatherization Assistance Program.
Arrangement
Recordings in Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral history were kept in the original order, arranged alphabetically by the narrator's last name.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Many oral histories can be accessed onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal.
Related Materials
In addition to this collection, Brooklyn Historical Society has many other records related to the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation and the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Among these are:
• Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation publication and photograph collection, 1968-2007, ARC.124
• Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council publications, 1965-1972, ARC.163
• Viola Hargrave collection of Bedford-Stuyvesant photographs, circa 1960s to 1970s, V1974.005
Also, narrator Pamela Green, formerly the Executive Director of the Weeksville Heritage Center, was recorded in the Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection, 2010 (2010.020). Narrator Ronald Shiffman, who helped conceive and launch Restoration, donated his papers to BHS in 2013 (2013.023). For more information on these and several other collections associated with Bedford-Stuyvesant, please visit our online finding aid portal.
Existence and Location of Copies
This oral history collection was duplicated for the offices of Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation in 2009.
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between people, all of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles and Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The oral histories that make up this collection were compiled by a team including an oral history program coordinator and oral history program intern at Brooklyn Historical Society and staff members at Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Project staff included Sady Sullivan (Oral History Program Coordinator), Bahati Williams (Oral History Program Intern), Brian Purnell, PhD (Researcher and Interviewer), Tracey Capers (Senior Vice President of Programs and Organizational Development - Restoration), Wendell Rice (Director of Weatherization Program - Restoration, and Interviewer), Judith Anglin (Human Resources Director - Restoration, and Interviewer), and Peggy Alston (Youth Arts Academy Director - Restoration, and Interviewer).
African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Exhibition records; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interviews (sound recordings); New York (N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Oral histories (document genres); Alston, Peggy; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Center for Art and Culture; Billie Holiday Theatre; Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; Grannum, Colvin W.; Inniss, Charles E.; Kennedy, Robert F.; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; Thomas, Franklin A.; Vann, Albert; Youth Arts Academy
- Alston, Peggy, 2008 January 28; 2008.030.01
  Biographical / Historical
  Peggy Alston grew up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She attended Medgar Evers College and was a founding member of the Billie Holiday Theatre Company. At the time of the interview, Alston was the Director for the Youth Arts Academy, a part of Restoration's Center for Arts and Culture that provided professional-level arts training to youth from Bedford-Stuyvesant and New York City.
  Scope and Contents
  Peggy Alston discusses her experiences growing up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She relates the importance of the arts in the development of children and adults, as well as the pedagogic philosophy of the Youth Arts Academy and her role as Director there. Alston observes the changes in Bedford-Stuyvesant and Restoration's role in its community. She also shows her appreciation for the arts in African-American culture and history. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Conditions Governing Access and Use
  Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cultural facilities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Alston, Peggy; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Billie Holiday Theatre; City University of New York. Medgar Evers College; Moon, Marjorie; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; Youth Arts Academy
- Baraka, Che, 2008 January 28; 2008.030.02
  Born in Chicago, Illinois in 1953, Che Baraka left his boyhood home in Jackson, Mississippi for New York City at age eighteen. After studying at the School of Visual Arts, Baraka became an art workshop instructor at Restoration's Youth Arts Academy in Brooklyn. Baraka's decades-long association with Restoration incorporates his roles as art instructor, curator, activist, and exhibiting artist. At the time of the 2008 interview, Baraka was a well-known mixed-media artist whose paintings had been exhibited nationally.
  In this interview, the artist Che Baraka recounts his childhood precocity in Jackson, Mississippi, where he became involved with the U.S. Civil Rights Movement that would later inform his work as an artist. Baraka recalls his escape from a culturally barren Jackson, Mississippi to join the arts scene of New York City, where he became situated within the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Baraka discusses his involvement with Restoration, where he worked as an arts teacher, administrator, curator, and exhibiting artist. Baraka explains his curatorial philosophy and the difficulties of financing public arts programs. He states his views on Bedford-Stuyvesant's culture circa 2008, his current arts projects; and his thoughts on Restoration's social role and legacy. Interview conducted by Peggy Alston.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Education, Higher |z New York (State) |z New York; Mississippi; Baraka, Che; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Center for Art and Culture; Design Works of Bedford-Stuyvesant (Firm); Gunn, Theodore; Inniss, Charles E.; School of Visual Arts (New York, N.Y.)
- Barnett-Keller, Mary, 2008 May 5; 2008.030.03
  Mary Barnett-Keller, born in 1938, was an employee of Restoration's finance division.
  Mary Burnett-Keller discusses her involvement with Restoration from 1967-1978 when her employer Owen Haige was made Director of Finance for Restoration. She recalls the social environment of Restoration's early years and its impact on the community citing the Home Improvement Program as its most successful and important endeavor. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Barnett-Keller, Mary; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation
- Bobb-Semple, Crystal, 2008 April 21; 2008.030.04
  Crystal Bobb-Semple was born and raised in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Educated primarily in New York's public schools, she left the city for college and her master's in Public Administration. Bobb-Semple's early career was spent in children's services and she was a co-founder of the Child Welfare Taskforce. In the year 2000, Bobb-Semple opened the neighborhood's Brownstone Books store with aid from Restoration's revolving loan fund. (The program was a cornerstone of Restoration's business revitalization efforts.) At the time of the 2008 interview, Bobb-Semple's Brownstone Books had been open for eight years.
  In this interview, Crystal Bobb-Semple remembers growing up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, and recounts childhood memories of Restoration. She discusses her decision to establish the Brownstone Books store, details the mentorship she's received from the Bedford-Stuyvesant Merchants' Association, shares her role in the Bedford-Stuyvesant Gateway Business Improvement District, and considers capitalism as a means of community development. She speaks of the effects of revitalization efforts on gentrification, displacement, and multiculturalism. Bobb-Semple describes her career journey from an early start in child welfare services to her current occupation as a bookseller and promoter of literacy. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Merchants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Segregation |z United States; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bobb-Semple, Crystal; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; Grannum, Colvin W.
- Braithwaite, Edmon, 2008 April 21; 2008.030.05
  Edmon Braithwaite (born 1959) was a businessman in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the 2008 interview, Braithwaite was the owner of two businesses, co-chairman for the steering committee for the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood Business Improvement District, vice president of the Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants' Association of Bedford-Stuyvesant, and a chairman of 1 Caribbean Radio.
  In this interview, Edmon Braithwaite details the responsibilities he's shouldered as a civic-minded businessman, his thoughts on community service, and describes his role in founding the Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants' Association of Bedford-Stuyvesant. Braithwaite explains the local Business Improvement District's goal of fostering an enticing shopping district to attract shoppers and support the neighborhood's economic revitalization. He discusses the benefits of prosperity and challenges charges of gentrification by citing a number of recent opportunities afforded local citizens by new small businesses. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 21st century; Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Braithwaite, Edmon; Dabu, Joel; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; Katz, Noah; Mitchell, Bernadette; Robinson, Annette (Annette M.); Vann, Albert
- Brown, Naeemah, 2008 May 12; 2008.030.06
  Raised in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, Naeemah Brown became a dance instructor and choreographer. At the time of the 2008 interview, she had served as the African dance instructor at Restoration's Youth Arts Academy for over two years.
  In this interview, Naeemah Brown discusses the small and deeply-interwoven African dance community of New York City. She talks of her connection to Restoration, and its impact on the lives of the residents of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood. Interview conducted by Anasa Scott.
  Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires permission from BHS by contacting library@brooklynhistory.org.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dancers |z New York (State) |z New York; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Brooklyn Academy of Music; Brown, Naeemah; Youth Arts Academy
- Brown, Sheila, 2008 May 14; 2008.030.07
  Sheila Brown grew up in Brooklyn and remained a resident as of the 2008 interview. She had been attending Restoration's money management workshops called Wealth Building Tuesdays.
  Familiar with the reputation of Restoration, Sheila Brown had little interaction with the community development entity until participating in the financial skill-building workshops offered by Restoration. Brown discusses how attending the Wealth Building Tuesdays sessions was a boon to her money management abilities. Interview conducted by Bernice McRae.
  Adult learning |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Finance |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home economics |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Brown, Sheila
- Carter, Ralph, 2008 January 18; 2008.030.08
  Ralph David Carter was born in 1961 in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn, one of an eventual seven children raised by his single mother. As a boy, Carter found work and fame as a child actor. At the age of twelve, he was nominated for a Tony Award in the best supporting actor category for his Broadway performance in the musical Raisin, based on the Lorraine Hansberry drama A Raisin in the Sun. It was his sixth Broadway show. Carter was popularly known for playing the role of Michael Evans on the CBS sitcom Good Times, which aired from 1974-1979; and for his 1975 album, the disco-era hit "When You're Young and in Love."
  In this interview, the singer, songwriter, actor, and playwright Ralph Carter discusses the historical roots of his childhood in the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn. He recalls the misunderstood nature of the Brownsville community, including the watchful eyes of vagrant people, and the cultural energy that encircled and influenced his development. He explains his religious or spiritual beliefs and social justice convictions. Carter lauds many of the important mentors in his career, with a particular emphasis on John Amos. Carter prescribes a didactic role for theater and the arts in providing positive Black role models to everyday Americans or depicting the horrors of drug addiction (as in the 1989 Judi Ann Mason play Donnie's House, in which Carter performed the leading role). He remembers the legacy of Restoration and its Billie Holiday Theatre for providing employment to Black performing artists, and intellectual entertainment for a Black audience. Carter expounds upon the importance of diversity in the theater, of cultural heritage institutions in early childhood development, and mentorship in artistic development. Interview conducted by Peggy Alston.
  Actors |z United States; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Cultural facilities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Theater |z New York (State) |z New York; Alston, Peggy; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Billie Holiday Theatre; Carter, Ralph David; Mason, Judi Ann; Moon, Marjorie; Robeson, Paul; Youth Arts Academy
- Charles, Kourtney, 2008 May; 2008.030.09
  Access to this recording is restricted by the donor. Please contact library@brooklynhistory.org for further questions.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Charles, Kourtney
- Dabu, Joel, 2008 April 11; 2008.030.10
  Joel Dabu was born in Norfolk, Virginia, in 1980, and attended New York University's Wagner Graduate School of Public Service, where he received a master's degree in Urban Planning. At the time of the 2008 interview, Dabu worked as a Commercial Revitalization Manager at Restoration, where his main task consisted of aiding in the revitalization of the Fulton Street and Nostrand Avenue business district.